<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sacramental-question concerning assurance how far necessary to a worthy communicant, practically answered, in a sermon, preparatory to the Lord's-Supper, Saturday, March 2, 1699/1700.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58940</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S223A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7898</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11902803</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11902803</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50599</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58940)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50599)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 509:40)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sacramental-question concerning assurance how far necessary to a worthy communicant, practically answered, in a sermon, preparatory to the Lord's-Supper, Saturday, March 2, 1699/1700.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 63 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Brudenell, for John Fawkner ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: J.S.</note>
                  <note>In MS. on t.p.: By Mr. Shower [or Showers]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:50599:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50599:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Sacramental-Queſtion Concerning ASSURANCE.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50599:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50599:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Sacramental-Queſtion CONCERNING ASSURANCE: How far Neceſſary to <hi>A Worthy Communicant,</hi> Practically Anſwered, in a SERMON, Preparatory to The Lord's-Supper.
<hi>Saturday, March</hi> 2. 1699/1700.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Brudenell,</hi> for <hi>John Fawkner,</hi> at the
<hi>Talbot,</hi> on the <hi>Bridge.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:50599:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50599:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>HAving reaſon to believe the following Diſcourſe was of ſome <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe to ſeveral who heard it, to comply with their Deſire, and in hope of doing good to Others, it is now Publiſh'd. If it be objected, That the Stile is too Negligent and Copious; and the ſame things expreſs'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and over in different Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſometimes the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, which may be well enough in Preaching to a mixt Auditory, but more exactneſs ſhould be uſed in Printing; I have only to ſay,
<pb facs="tcp:50599:4"/> That I apprehend the ſame Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit Stile will beſt anſwer my End, as to the Service of thoſe, for whom I principally intend it.</p>
            <p>May I find Mercy of the Lord to be Faithful, whoſe I am, and to whom I am devoted! If any are brought upon their Knees, ſeriouſly to bleſs God, for what they Heard, or ſhall now Read, I ſhall more heartily Rejoyce in it, than to have the Approbation and Applauſe of all the
<hi>Witty People</hi> upon Earth, who have not <hi>Wiſdom</hi> enough to know themſelves, and conſider their latter End, and prepare for Death and Judgment, which cannot be without ſeeking to Jeſus Christ, as the only Redeemer and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb facs="tcp:50599:4"/> of Sinners, to reconcile us to God, and ſave us from Wrath to come. His Grace, and Mercy, and Love, is above all we can think. Oh be Humble and Thankful; adore Him, and admire His rich, free, and glorious Grace, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it not!</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. S.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April 17. 1700.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50599:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50599:5"/>
            <head>A Sacramental-Queſtion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ASSURANCE, How far neceſſary to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Receiving.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. XI. 28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>— But let a Man Examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that Bread. —</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this Verſe you have it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppos'd, That 'tis a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an's Duty to partake of the Lord's-Supper. The manner of the Performance is regulated, but the ſubſtance of the Duty is preſuppos'd, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>Do this in remembrance of Chriſt.</hi> He ought to eat of this Bread, and drink of this Cup, and ſhew forth the Lord's Death this way; only take heed not to ruſh haſtily, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out previous Self-Examination.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:50599:6"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. That ſolemn Preparation is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the right performance of this Duty, may be argued from the Inſtance given of one ſpecial part of that Preparation, The due Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of our ſelves. <hi>Let a Man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that Bread.</hi> — 'Tis a Chriſtian's Duty to partake of this Solemn Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance: He muſt not do it raſhly and unpreparedly: And it is one ſpecial Part of neceſſary Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to Examine himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> But ſome will be ready to ſay, <hi>I have Examin'd my ſelf, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to know the true ſtate of my Soul, but I cannot come to a Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; Whether I have Sacramental Graces in truth, and am partaker of Life from the Spirit of Christ, or no; and conſequently, how is it my Duty to come to this Ordinance for Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Nouriſhment? After all my Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, I cannot poſitively conclude, that I am in a ſtate of Grace; at leaſt, I have many Doubts and Fears; I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50599:6"/> have no Certainty, no Aſſurance of my good Eſtate towards God. May I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs come? Is it my Duty, while I have ſo many Doubts and Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties unreſolv'd, and am ſo far from full Aſſurance and Joy?</hi> This I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to Anſwer, by conſidering how far Aſſurance is neceſſary to our Worthy Receiving: You will have my Thoughts of it, in the following Particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. First,</hi> That in the diligent uſe of God's appointed means; it may ordinarily be known, Whether you have truly Repented of your Sins, and do unfeignedly Believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: And ſo, whether you are ſincere in your Chriſtian Profeſſion, or no. By Self-Reflection, and comparing your ſelves with the Word of God, endeavouring to prove your ſelves, and making uſe of the Aſſiſtance of Books, and Miniſters, with Prayer to God, to enable you to diſcern the true ſtate of your Caſe, you may ordinarily come to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50599:7"/> the knowledge of your ſelves, and your Spiritual Condition. I ſpeak not of the groſly Ignorant, or of ſuch as live at that rate of Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that they cannot but know they are Impenitent, or may eaſily know it on a little Reflexion, but of ſuch as doubt, and have ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He that endeavours not to know the true ſtate of his Soul, that with a prepared Heart he may joyn with his Brethren and Fellow Chriſtians, at the Table of the Lord, liveth in continual Sin. He that will not endeavour to come Worthily, and accordingly Examine himſelf, that he may be diſpos'd, and fitted for this Ordinance, he continueth to diſobey an Order of Chriſt. 'Tis not enough to ſay you have no <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance,</hi> or are afraid to come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it; that will not excuſe you from Sin. Many keep off, on ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, leſt they ſhould Eat and Drink Unworthily, and ſo Sin: But conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50599:7"/> not the Sin and Danger on the other hand, of ſtaying away, upon ſuch grounds as will not excuſe them before God. Conſider therefore what is the faulty cauſe of your Ignorance of your ſelves, and of your true ſtate towards God? Is it not Sloth and Careleſsneſs, Negligence and Remiſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Earthly Cares, or the Hurry of Worldly Buſineſs? And if the doubts of your Sincerity ariſe from a faulty Cauſe, you muſt not plead thoſe Doubts, as a ſufficient Excuſe for not coming to the Lord's Table.</p>
            <p>There is a faulty Careleſsneſs in ſome good Chriſtians, that they do not obſerve and record the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God's Spirit upon their Hearts, and ſo <hi>the time of His Love</hi> is not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of, nor remembred. To allude to what God ſays to <hi>Ephraim,</hi> Hoſ. xi.
3. When <hi>Ephraim</hi> was a Child, I taught him to Go, taking him by the Arm, but <hi>he knew it not,</hi> did not obſerve it. You muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect, enquire, and conſider what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50599:8"/> God hath wrought in you, and done for you: Whether you have been brought, humbly to acknowledge your Sin with Shame and Sorrow and Self-abhorrence, ſeeing your need of Chriſt, and His Grace, have been perſwaded thankfully to take hold of the Covenant, to accept the offered Mercy of the Goſpel, and yield your ſelves to be the Lord's. We loſe much of our Comfort, for want of bringing our Doubts to a Determination; and this through La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zineſs, Sloth and Careleſsneſs. 'Tis true, the want of <hi>Aſſurance</hi> will not argue a Man under the Power of Unbelief, but it ſhews the Weakneſs of Faith; and we ought diligently to clear it up, whether we are in the Faith, and whether Chriſt be in us, or no; and whether with all our Hearts we love Him? Which, for the moſt part, may be known, as well as our Love and Affection to Perſons and Things, in other Caſes. If we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50599:8"/> reflect and bethink our ſelves, we may ordinarily know, that we Love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">Are you not willing that Chriſt ſhould be your Saviour, and bring you to Heaven, in God's appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted way? Do you not make Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion your great Buſineſs in this World? Is not your being accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God, in Chriſt, your great Concern? Is there any thing in all the World your Hearts are ſet more upon, than that you may be Saved by Jeſus Chriſt, and not be found Hypocrites at laſt? Would you not account the Certainty and Aſſurance of this, a greater Privilege, than to be Owner of all the Riches and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Earth? Is it not your heavieſt Burden, that you fear you ſhall fall ſhort of Heaven? And you dread nothing more, than to be miſtaken about your Intereſt in the ſpecial Love of God? Whence have you theſe Apprehenſions, theſe Deſires, this Choice? Can the Devil ever perſwade you this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50599:9"/> is from corrupt Nature; or, that that you don't love God, when you would give all the World to be aſſur'd of His Love? You ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor every thing that you think will diſpleaſe him: There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing he requires, but, by His Grace, you are willing to comply with: You would fain love, and ſerve, and enjoy Him better: There is nothing would better pleaſe or more rejoyce you, than to pleaſe Him more, and to be more conform'd to His Image, be fill'd with His Spirit, and live to Glorifie Him more in the World: There is no Luſt that you would indulge, but deſire to mortifie; and are accordingly diligent in the uſe of Chriſt's appointed Means, to ſubdue Corruption: 'Tis your Trouble and your Complaint, that you are not more Dead to Sin and the World; you feel the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Ignorance, Pride, Selfiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Carnality, Unbelief, Dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50599:9"/> Dulneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You groan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der 'em, as a continual Burden; and would rather be rid of 'em, than of any outward Affliction whatſoever. Doth not all this argue true Love to God and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; true Love to Chriſt, and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of Sin? And can you not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from hence, What he hath done for you, and wrought in your Souls? Oh bear not falſe Witneſs againſt your Selves! But labour, by ſuch Reflections, to know your State, that you may come to the Table of the Lord, with Joy and Praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As it is ordinarily ſome Sin that keeps a Man unreſolv'd, and in the dark (which doth not excuſe him from the Duty) ſo for a Man to miſtake his true State, and doubt and queſtion his Integrity towards God (if he be <hi>Sincere</hi>) even that Doubt is his Sin.</p>
            <p>He ought to endeavour to know himſelf, and make a right judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50599:10"/> and then come to receive the Seal of the Covenant. His miſtake in judging of his own Caſe, is faulty, and will not excuſe him from the obligation of judging more truly and juſtly of himſelf. Upright Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are oblig'd to judge of themſelves according to Truth, what really they are, and ſo to receive what belongs to them, as the Children of God, and Members of Chriſt, within the Bond of the Everlaſting Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> 'Tis a common and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous miſtake (by which many are deceived) to place the nature of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, Juſtifying Faith, in the Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God's Love; and the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Perſwaſion that we are Pardon'd, and Juſtify'd, and Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God: Whereas, many truly Believe, and have Faith unfeigned, and ſhall inherit Eternal Life, who yet doubt and fear, and dare not ſay all this; and others may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that is their Caſe, who did never yet Believe in Chriſt, with all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50599:10"/> their Hearts: The one ſhall be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of their Fears, as the other of their Hopes.</p>
            <p>To place Faith in a meer Aſſent to the Doctrin of the Goſpel, is one Extreme; to place it in aſſurance of my good Eſtate towards God, that's another. There is a Bleſſedneſs pronounc'd to ſuch as Mourn, and are Poor in Spirit, and Hunger and Thirſt after Righteouſneſs: They may do ſo without Aſſurance. The Unbelief that Condems, is not the not Believing we are already Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; therefore the Faith which Saves Men, is not the believing that they are Juſtified. He that believes he is Juſtify'd and Pardon'd, muſt be ſo, before he can believe it. <hi>By him all that believe are Juſtified,</hi> Acts xiii. 39.
<hi>We have believed in Jeſus Christ, that we might be juſtified,</hi> Gal. ii. 16. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance follows Faith: <hi>In whom after ye believed, you were Sealed with the Holy Spirit of Promiſe,</hi> 1 Eph. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50599:11"/>All that hear the Goſpel Preach'd are commanded to Believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; but all are not commanded or obliged to believe their Sins are already pardon'd, and that they are in a juſtify'd State; then many would be commanded to believe what is not yet true. And to believe my Sins are forgiven, that they may be forgiven, is very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd: And yet, if Faith be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Juſtification, this will follow. To believe I ſhall certainly be Sav'd, is not juſtifying Faith. I muſt be ſo juſtified before I can believe it, or be aſſured of it. The Scripture makes a plain difference between theſe two, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> v.
13. <hi>Theſe things have I writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to you, who believe on the Name of the Son of God, that ye may know ye have Eternal Life;</hi> that is, have it in the Seed, and Root, in the Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and Beginning of it. They might have ſaid, we do this already, if Faith conſiſt in believing I am Pardon'd, and ſhall be Saved. And
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50599:11"/> many that have had Aſſurance, have loſt it, as well as many, who have true Faith, may not have reached Aſſurance. I ſay, many have loſt Aſſurance who have not loſt their Faith; unleſs a Man may be a Believer and no Believer ſeveral times in a Year. There are ſeveral States, Ages, and Ranks of Believers; ſome whereof are yet ſhort of Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. And muſt not the Child be allow'd to be a Child, before he can ſpeak for himſelf, and ſay he is one? How many of the Children of God muſt we then turn out of Doors, whom he receives and loves?</p>
            <p>Some of the firſt Reformers, who fell into this miſtake, were Eminent for Faith, and Holineſs, and Joy; and by what they found in themſelves (ſpeaking what they felt) they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed <hi>Faith,</hi> by ſuch a full Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Love of God, as many real Chriſtians have not attain'd; by ſuch Aſſurance and Joy of Faith, as they themſelves experienc'd: But
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50599:12"/> the Lord knoweth who are His, when many of them do not know it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.
'Tis the Reality and the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of our Faith that is neceſſary to Salvation, not the certain Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that Sincerity.</p>
            <p>I dare not come, ſays One and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, to the Table of the Lord, becauſe <hi>I can't Believe.</hi> I have not true and ſaving Faith. I can't Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve: But I would ask ſuch, What is it you can't Believe? <hi rend="margQuotes">Don't you Believe the Witneſs given by Chriſt, in the Holy Scriptures, to be true? Don't you Believe Him to be the true Meſſiah, the only Saviour of Sinners? That he hath Ability and Willingneſs to ſave to the Utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, All that come to God by Him? That He is Conſtituted and Impower'd, by Office, to do this, as the Chriſt of God? Don't you Believe, from your Hearts, that he is able to Reconcile you to God? That His Blood can Cleanſe from all Sin? That you are loſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50599:12"/> without Him? That if ever you are Reconcil'd, Pardon'd and Sav'd, it muſt be by Him? Don't you deſire this above all things? Are you not willing to take Him as your Saviour and Lord in all His Offices; to be taught by His Word, to be guided by His Spirit, to be govern'd by His Law, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on His Righteouſneſs, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and Interceſſion, for all your Hopes of Acceptance with God? Don't you look for all your Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of Grace and Strength, to conquer Temptation, and perform every Duty from His Spirit, as the Purchaſe of His Blood? Don't you Believe all the Promiſes He hath made, ſhall be fulfill'd? and deſire nothing more than that you may have a Share and Intereſt in the Bleſſings of the New Covenant, purchaſed and promiſed by Chriſt? And from your very Souls, are willing to be His, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any terms; ſo that, there is no Sin but you would be free from,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50599:13"/> rather than keep; and accordingly are faithful and conſtant in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You can't deny this; and yet, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, you'll ſay, you have no <hi>Faith,</hi> becauſe no
<hi>Aſſurance.</hi> Doth not all this argue true Faith? You want the Knowledge of your true State; but you don't want true Faith in Chriſt. Therefore you ought to come to the Table. Nay, tho' you have not conquer'd all your Doubts about the great Truths of the Goſpel; and the Life to come; and the Mediation of Chriſt; if yet you have ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Perſwaſion of thoſe Truths, as brings you to conſent to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace; to take God for for your God, and Chriſt for your only Saviour; and the Holy Ghoſt for your Sanctifier and Guide; His Law for your Rule, His Promiſe for your Security, and the Heavenly Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for your Reſt and Happineſs; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving, by the Grace of God, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all that ſtands in Competition;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50599:13"/> you are <hi>True Believers,</hi> and ought to come, to Eat of the Children's Bread.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> There is a vaſt difference, as to the Lord's Supper, between the Caſe of an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> who does not know himſelf to be one, and the Caſe of a ſincere, real Chriſtian, who doth not know himſelf to be <hi>Sincere.</hi> You muſt not imagine theſe two Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to be alike: The one has true Grace, tho' he diſcern it not, and conſequently hath a right to the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the Covenant, and is bound to know and diſcern his Title, and ſo come and partake of the Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that belong to his State. But ſuppoſe another Profeſſor comes to the Lord's Table, who hath no true Repentance, or Faith, and ſo his Heart not right with God, but he is under the Reign, Power, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of Sin. He hath, as yet, no right to the Bleſſings of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; but is bound to know his true State, that he may be brought to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50599:14"/> Repentance; 'tis a greater Sin for him do demand, and take what doth not belong to him, than to tarry away for a while, in order to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery and Preparation: For, if ſuch a one comes, he Hypocritically pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes that Repentance, Faith and Devoutneſs to God, which he hath nothing of, but is ſecretly an Enemy to God and Holineſs: He comes and claims the Childrens Bread, with a Lye in his Mouth and Heart, againſt the Holy Ghoſt; and he takes the Name of God in vain. There is a great difference in this Caſe, from that of a doubting Chriſtian, who truly Believes, and cannot ſay he is aſſured of it. There is a further difference, in point of Comfort; for a real Chriſtian, tho' he come with many Doubts and Fears, yet there are ſome ſecret. Teſtimonies of the Love of God; there is ſome Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Holy Spirit to bear up his Hope; which is much better than all the groundleſs Joys of Hypocrites,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50599:14"/> in a falſe perſwaſion of the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their State.</p>
            <p>The Penitent, Upright Believer, who wants Aſſurance, hath a right to the Ordinance, and is accepted with God, tho' he can't affirm it; or ſay, that he unfeignedly Believes in Chriſt, and Loves God with all his Heart, yet he hopes 'tis true: He is willing to be the Lord's on his own terms. 'Tis the favour of God in Chriſt that he values, and ſeeks above all things: This he aims at; nothing elſe will content him; he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in it, more than in any Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Proſperity, if he could attain more certain knowledge of it. Is not ſuch a one accepted of God? And ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a competency of knowledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the nature of the Sacrament, (to underſtand his Work, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Lord's Body,) he hath a right to come; tho' his timerous Scruples may keep him off a while, yet they can't deprive him of his Right, or diſoblige him from his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50599:15"/> Duty, to ſhew forth the Lord's Death this way. He doth truly conſent to the Covenant, and ſhould come to ſignifie that Conſent, and receive the Seal of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>And remember this, That the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace is mutual between God and You; ſo that, from your Conſent to be the Lord's, you may infer that He is <hi>Your God:</hi> Your choice of Him is an Evidence of your Intereſt in Him by a Covenant-Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Relation is mutual,
<hi>equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and at <hi>once,</hi> on both ſides; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as <hi>ſoon,</hi> and as
<hi>long,</hi> as you can ſay,
<q>Lord, <hi>I am Thine,</hi> and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to abide, continue Thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, I would not depart from Thee.</q> As ſoon, and as long as you find within you ſuch a Diſpoſition of Heart, you may be aſſur'd that <hi>God is your God,</hi> and will be your God for Ever, and Guide unto Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> There is a true diſcerning of our Faith and Repentance, which is ſhort of Aſſurance, upon which we
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50599:15"/> may act, tho' we are not fully cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. There is true Love to Chriſt, that is ſhort of delighting and rejoyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love; even deſiring and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Love: Tho' there be not the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Seal of the Holy Spirit to give Joy, there may be ſo much know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our good Eſtate attain'd in a way of Duty, as to prevent trouble and terror of Mind; even <hi>a good Hope, through Grace,</hi> ſhort of Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and full of Perſwaſion.</p>
            <p>And, if a Man may not act upon ſome good Hopes (tho' he have not an aſſured certain Judgment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his State) a great deal of God's Service in the Chriſtian Church would be laid aſide. For Inſtance, He only that's Penitent, ſhould profeſs himſelf Penitent; only he that truly deſires Chriſt and His Grace, ſhould ſay he doth deſire it; only they that have received Saving Grace, ſhould give God thanks for having received it: And yet, if none ſhould confeſs Sin, and profeſs Repentance, but ſuch as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50599:16"/> knew certainly, and with Aſſurance, that they are truly Penitent; and if none ſhould beg Grace, with a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion that they deſire it, till they have Aſſurance of the truth of thoſe Deſires; if none ſhould give Thanks to God for Redemption, Effectual Calling, Juſtification, Adoption and Sanctification, but ſuch as have full Aſſurance, that they have received all theſe; there would be little Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Prayer, and Thankſgiving in the Chriſtian World. Is it unlawful to ſay, I Believe, while there is a mixture of Unbelief? We muſt let alone a great part of our Religion, if we may not act upon Hope, ſhort of Aſſurance. And if all doubting trembling Chriſtians ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barr'd the Lord's Table, till they have Certainty and Aſſurance, there would not only be very few to partake of it; but we ſhould exclude ſome of the fitteſt, the moſt acceptable, and moſt welcom Gueſts at that Feaſt of Love. Therefore we may have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50599:16"/> Fears, and Scruples, yet if Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, enlightned by the Word of God, do not poſitively condemn us, (tho' upon Self-Examination, it doth not clearly and fully abſolve us,) we may come in Hope.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Tho' you have not yet attain'd Aſſurance of the Love of God, and of your reconciled, juſtified State; yet, by waiting on God, in the uſe of His Holy Ordinances, you may expect and hope to attain it. You may and ought to wait for, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications of His Grace and Love, in the uſe of all His Appointed Means; and 'tis one End and Uſe of <hi>The Lord's-Supper,</hi> to ſtrengthen weak Faith, and to help doubting Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. You have there a Sign, and Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith: The Blood of Chriſt is there repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as ſhed for the Remiſſion of your Sins: The Benefits of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption are offer'd to you in particular; and you are called to apply them to yourſelf, as if your Names were men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50599:17"/> You are there call'd to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs your Acceptance of Chriſt, and the offer'd Salvation of the Goſpel; and to ſurrender, and give back your ſelves entirely to be the Lord's. This Feaſt was not appointed only for thoſe, who are the moſt perfect Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and higheſt in Grace; but for the Relief and Supply of your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Wants: You come there not only to be Thankful for what Grace you have received, but to receive more. What would you think if one ſhould tell you, You muſt not eat, till your Hunger be firſt ſatisfy'd; or not come to the Fire, till you are firſt Warm; or not take Phyſick, till you have recover'd your Health? The Seals of the Covenant are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for our greater Confirmation, that the Heirs of the Promiſe might have more abundant Conſolation and Joy: And, in this Ordinance, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Speaks more ſolemnly, more, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, and more pathetically to us, for the help of our Faith, than by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50599:17"/> the Miniſtry of the Word. What is ſpoken in general, by the Preaching of the Word, is here particularly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd to individual Perſons; to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Weak and Doubting Chriſtians, as well as to confirm the Joy of their Stronger Brethren. You may as well neglect hearing the Word, and pray and hope for Faith, as expect Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and neglect the Lord's Table. The Primitive Chriſtians, who walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Fear of God, and in the Comforts of the Holy Ghoſt, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the practice of breaking the holy Bread (partaking of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance) and ſo could Eat their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Meat with gladneſs of Heart, praiſing God. It may be you'll find, as <hi>Jeſus</hi> made Himſelf known to the two Diſciples <hi>in breaking of Bread,</hi> (to allude to that Expreſſion, tho' I think it not meant of Sacramental Bread,) ſo you may find, by waiting on God in this Ordinance, your Doubts ſcatter'd, your Jealouſies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, your Difficulties clear'd, your
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50599:18"/> Objections anſwer'd, and the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your State, which before was doubtful, made manifeſt and evident, to the Joy of your Souls.</p>
            <p>Therefore refuſe not o pay Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to your Crucify'd Saviour, by partaking of this Ordinance, believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that you ſhall not do it in vain: It may be, e'er you are aware, your Souls ſhall be, as the Chariots of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minadab;</hi> you can't tell but your At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance on this Inſtitution, ſhall be the happy means, which God will make uſe of to ſcatter and cure your Doubts. And, by your neglect of this Ordinance, you not only take the moſt likely courſe to increaſe and continue your Doubts and Fears, but are in danger to loſe that Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Spirit, and ſenſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which you now have, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying your ſelf thoſe Means and Helps, by which it is preſerv'd and maintain'd in other Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Conſider, that after Self-Examination, you may ſometimes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50599:18"/> find one Grace more evident than an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. A Chriſtian can ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, more hopefully, that he lives by Faith; ſometimes that he has true
<hi>Repentance,</hi> and Godly Sorrow for Sin; ſometimes he can ſay more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the truth of his <hi>Love to Chriſt;</hi> ſometimes concerning his <hi>Hunger</hi> and <hi>Thirst</hi> after Chriſt, and the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality and Earneſtneſs of his <hi>Deſires:</hi> And if you can diſcover Truth and Integrity of Heart, as to any of theſe, you may ſo far take Comfort. But eſpecially, as to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> the two Radical Graces, which do influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſtrengthen all others; and by which you may make the beſt judgment of your ſelf.</p>
            <p>And a difference you muſt allow, for different Times and Seaſons. Tho', it may be, you cannot <hi>now</hi> ſay ſo much concerning this or the other particular Grace; yet, at ſuch a time, upon ſerious Reflection, you could ſay a great deal to the Glory of God, and to your own Conſolation; you
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50599:19"/> think that it is much better <hi>now</hi> with others than with you; but it may be the laſt Month, at the laſt Sacrament, you could ſay truly, concerning your Communion with God, and the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of His Love, and the Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your own, and the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of other Graces, a great deal more, than any of thoſe Chriſtians and Brethren, whom you apprehend to be ſo much above and before you.</p>
            <p>Remember, how at ſuch a time, according to ſuch a Scripture Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of an Upright Chriſtian, your Hearts could bear witneſs, and God did bear witneſs, by his Spirit, that you were not Hypocrites. Did you not record it? Did you not promiſe to remember it, and improve it? Call to mind what hath paſs'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and your Souls, as to ſuch things: And, if there be no notable declining to the World and the Fleſh, or commiſſion of groſs Sins, or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Careleſsneſs or Remiſsneſs, (which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50599:19"/> muſt be particularly repented of, and reform'd, in order to Pardon, and Peace,) you may take comfort in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Evidences, and Experience. If a Father have forgiven a Child that had offended him, and told him ſo; muſt he be every day telling him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and again, that he hath forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, or he won't believe it? If God hath comfortably reſolv'd your Doubts, tho' ſome time ſince, you may be encourag'd by it; for you have not alway the ſame Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity or Help, outward or inward, to diſcern aright the State of your Soul; not alway the ſame clearneſs of Apprehenſion, or ſedateneſs of Mind, or Aſſiſtance of God's Spirit, to determine and reſolve the great Queſtion. 'Tis unreaſonable, on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very turn, to expect a new Anſwer from God; as if he had given you none before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> As to the Apoſtle's Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is frequently objected in this caſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> xiv. 24. <hi>He that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50599:20"/> doubteth is damned, if he eat, becauſe he eateth not in Faith; and what is not of Faith is Sin.</hi> You ought to conſider, that the Word we render <hi>Doubting,</hi> is
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, making a <hi>difference</hi> between <hi>Clean,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean</hi> Meats: 'Tis not meant of Eating at the Lord's Table, but of Eating thoſe Meats, which were forbidden by the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Jews;</hi> or ſuch as had been offer'd to Idols, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſold in the Market: Meats to be Eaten at an ordinary Table, concerning which, one who believ'd the Obligation of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> thought to be
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean.</hi> He was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the Unlawfulneſs of Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but he knows he may Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbare. This is quite another matter, than the caſe of an ordinary doubting Conſcience; where a Man only doubts on one ſide of an Action. 'Tis there but reaſonable to chuſe that ſide, where he hath no doubt, rather than the other, where he ſuſpects he may tranſgreſs ſome Law of God,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50599:20"/> tho' he be not certain. While the Doubt laſts, till a Man be better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, (ſuppoſing he be miſtaken,) he ſhould forbear acting againſt his preſent Opinion, and Judgment: <hi>Whatſoever is not of Faith, is Sin,</hi> i. e. Whatever a Man doth, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſwaded of the Lawfulneſs of it, tho' it be not a Sin in it ſelf, it is ſo to him, who doth it againſt his Conſcience. But as to matter of <hi>plain Duty,</hi> ſuch as, Doing this in Remembrance of Chriſt, and ſhewing forth His Death, by coming to His Table, it is otherwiſe. The Doubt will not excuſe him in the neglect of his Duty: His Doubt is double, whether he be not bound, by the Command of Chriſt, to Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate; but on the other ſide, he doubts whether, by ſome other Law of God, he ought not, as yet, to forbear, as not thinking himſelf duly qualified. In ſuch a caſe, What ſhould a Man do, but endeavour to fit, prepare, and qualifie himſelf, as ſoon, and as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50599:21"/> well as he can; that he may not continue to offend God, by the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Obedience to an Order of Chriſt. And can ſuch a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne ſay, he is as certain he is not qualified to come, as he is certain, in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that it is his Duty to come?</p>
            <p>As to the Expreſſion, <hi>He is Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned if he Eat:</hi> The meaning is, He is Self-condemn'd, his Conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns him; for he knows 'tis lawful to forbear; and he believes it to be unlawful to Eat: If he do Eat, he acts againſt his own Judgment, and ſo is Self-condemn'd. As to matter of Duty, an Erring Conſcience, be ſure, will not cancel the Obligation of the Law of God: If we doubt concerning that, which God hath made our Duty; our Doubt will not excuſe us from Sin; for God hath bound us to know our Duty and do it. Whatever our Opinion and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion be, the Obligation to obey the Command of God remains: Our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50599:21"/> doubting whether it be our Duty, doth not make it ceaſe to be ſo.</p>
            <p>However ſome Melancholy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, under great Conflicts and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, may ſuſpend and ſtay away for a while, leſt they ſhould run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Deſpair, on the Apprehenſion of having Eaten and Drank their own Damnation. They ought not to cheriſh ſuch Doubts and Fears, but endeavour to overcome them, and ask Advice and Counſel, and uſe all other fit means in order to it; that, being better acquainted with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they may come with Peace and Comfort. If your Hearts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to be the Lord's, according to the tenor of the Covenant of Grace, you ought to come, and Declare that Conſent, with your Fellow Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> Conſider that there is a <hi>Scrupulous Conſcience,</hi> which tho' re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd and ſatisfy'd, in the main, concerning Duty, when it comes to act, is perplex'd and hindred by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable Fears. Tho' there be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50599:22"/> no juſt, rational, Scripture Grounds of Fear or Doubt, yet a Perſon of weak Parts, little Knowledge, and of a timerous Diſpoſition, is eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted with general Jealouſies and Fears, as to himſelf and his ſtate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God. He fears (tho' he can't tell particularly from the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures why) that he is not qualify'd, that he ſhall receive unworthily if he come, and eat and drink Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to himſelf: Ask why he thinks ſo, He has only ſome conjectural Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picions, ſome uncertain Surmiſes of his own Condition, ariſing from ſome miſtaken Notions of the Qualications, and Preparation neceſſary to a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Communicant. Theſe general; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptual Doubts, Jealouſies, and Fears, if countenanc'd and indulg'd, will increaſe, and, like Circles in the Water, continue and beget one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But a good Man would not deal with his Neighbour, after this manner, as with himſelf: He would not, he ought not, to judge hardly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50599:22"/> of a Neighbour, by general Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of Accuſation, or every idle Objection, and imaginary Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that may be made to his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, if, when particularly Enquired into, ſolid and poſitive Proof is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. You muſt not judge hardly of your ſelves, any more than favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, but according to the Word of God, the Rule of Judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> If you have not Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, yet if your Hearts accuſe you not of Hypocriſie, and double Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; if you can ſay, As far as I know my own Heart and Life, I think I do ſincerely conſent to the Covenant of Grace, and am really chang'd as to my Principles and Ends; I am unfeignedly willing, without reſerve, to be the Lord's; You may come, to renew and ſeal your Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Can you ſay,
<q>I believe the Goſpel to be true; I am willing to have <hi>Christ</hi> for my <hi>Saviour</hi> and <hi>Lord,</hi> and abſolutely to reſign my ſelf to Him; to be rul'd by His
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50599:23"/> Laws, and ſav'd by His Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: My Imperfections I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail, my Corruptions I ſtrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and endeavour to Mortifie; and, as far as I know my ſelf, am willing to part with every known Sin: I am not certain, I am a true Believer, but I would fain be deliver'd, by Chriſt, from the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of Sin, as well as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of it.</q> Now, where the Caſe is thus, what ſhould be a bar to your coming to the Lord's Table? Such a ſenſe of Sin, and ſtriving againſt it, and deſire to be rid of it, is your ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Fitneſs. And in this, as well as other caſes, we may act according to the beſt of our Judgment, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſome conſiderable Doubts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> You may come with Humility and Reverence, paying Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to a Crucify'd Saviour, having found <hi>your Sins,</hi> and being humbled and penitent, judging and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelves for <hi>'em;</hi> tho' you have not ſo clearly diſcover'd <hi>your Graces,</hi> as to be able to Rejoyce, you
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50599:23"/> may come with broken and contrite Hearts, as <hi>Penitent Sinners,</hi> if you can't come with Aſſurance, that you are <hi>Pardon'd Sinners;</hi> you may come, ſenſible of <hi>your need of Christ,</hi> if you can't come with the clear knowledge of <hi>your Interest in Him.</hi> Come with Humility and Contrition of <hi>Return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Penitents,</hi> tho' you can't come with the Joy of Faith, as <hi>Aſſured Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</hi> Come with Hunger and Thirſt after Chriſt, and His Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, tho' you dare not yet ſay, <hi>My Beloved is mine, and I am His.</hi> Come humbly, and Apply yourſelves to Him as you can, if you can't Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Him to your ſelves as you would. Honour Him as <hi>your Lord,</hi> when you can't appropriate Him to your ſelf, as <hi>your Saviour.</hi> Own His Propriety in you, tho' you are not aſſured of your Intereſt in Him. Come, and ſay, <hi>Lord, I Believe, help my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief!</hi> If you can't triumphantly ſay, <hi>He Lov'd me, and Dyed for me:</hi> You can't, with <hi>Certainty,</hi> ſay, <hi>He is Mine;</hi> but you can ſay it, with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50599:24"/> 
               <hi>Sincerity,</hi> that you deſire to be <hi>His:</hi> You reſolve to be ſo, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly give up your ſelves to Him. Lord, help me; Lord, ſave me; Lord, ſtrengthen me; Lord, deliver me, for <hi>I am Thine,</hi> as the <hi>Pſalmist</hi> frequently ſpeaks. You may uſe ſuch Language; <hi>Lord, I am Thine,</hi> Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Dedicated, Reſigned, Willing to be <hi>Thine,</hi> tho', I can't ſay, with preſent Joy and Comfort, (what that truly infers,) That <hi>He is Mine.</hi> You can ſay, <hi>Lord.</hi> If I am rejected, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd, caſt off, and left to Periſh, there ſhall One Periſh, who did heartily and unfeignedly Deſire to be the Lord's: But, you may be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that ſuch ſhall never Periſh, if they follow on to know the Lord, and ſeek him.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore bring this home to <hi>Doubting, Trembling Chriſtians,</hi> who are afraid to tarry away from the Lord's Table, and yet, for want of <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> are doubtful, whether they ſhould come or no. You have
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50599:24"/> Examin'd your ſelves, and found out your Sins, ſo as to be humbled for them: You are among ſuch as <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> and <hi>Thirst;</hi> you can't deny it: And is not
<hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> promiſed to ſuch? <hi>Matth.</hi> v. 6. You are in the Number of ſuch as are <hi>weary and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy laden</hi> for Sin; and is there not <hi>Rest</hi> promiſed to the Souls of ſuch? <hi>Matth.</hi> xi. 29. The Bleſſings of the Covenant have been offer'd to you; you conſent to the Terms on which they are propos'd, and deſire to truſt in Chriſt to do all this for you, which he hath promiſed: Why ſhould not you come and Seal this at the Lord's Table, and profeſs this to be the Senſe of your Hearts? Is all this no Evidence of Faith? You may have true unfeigned Faith, tho' you don't know certainly that it is true. If Sin be a Burthen, and you are weary of it, and would fain have it more ſubdu'd, and you ong for more Conformity to Chriſt, that the ſame Spirit may be in you, that was in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50599:25"/> Him; If you long to have the Love of Chriſt rule and reign more in your Souls; If it be thus, you may come in Hope, and plead his Word, and pray for His Grace, and devote and give up your ſelves to be the Lords. You may do this Acceptably at His Table, without a certain Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, and aſſured Knowledge, that you are paſſed from Death to Life, and made an Heir of Heaven. Tho' you have ſome Fears of Hypocriſie, you dare not ſay, but you have ſome Hopes that you are Sincere; and a mixture of ſome Fear with your Hope ſhould not diſcourage you. Doubts concerning the Truth of your Faith, are very conſiſtent with the Reality of it: The ſhaking of a Tree, will not argue it is not a Tree, or not Alive.</p>
            <p>Our Lord hath told you, He is willing to be your Saviour; I tell you again, that He is Willing to be <hi>Yours,</hi> in all His Offices, as <hi>Prophet, Priest, and King:</hi> He hath done and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50599:25"/> ſuffer'd enough (one would think) to teſtifie His Willingneſs, to declare His Love, and expreſs His Kindneſs and Good-will. Can you think of His Bloody Death and Sufferings, and queſtion His Willingneſs to Receive, and Pardon, and Save Sinners? Now, dare you deny, that you are <hi>willing to be His?</hi> To forſake all Compedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Rivals, and accept Him for your <hi>only Saviour?</hi> If you are <hi>heartily Willing;</hi> you are accepted, you are united to Chriſt, and intereſted in Him; And will you not lift up your Heads in Hope? Will you ſtill che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh unſcriptural, unreaſonable Doubts, that have no foundation in the Word of God? Will you continue to doubt of His Love, tho' you can't deny the Evidence of it? Do you not love Him ſo, that you can part with All, in this World, to be aſſur'd of His Love; and the want of this Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Aſſurance, is the daily Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of your Hearts, and the Matter of your continual Complaint? If He
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50599:26"/> ſhould ask you, as He did <hi>Peter,</hi> this Evening, or to Morrow Morning, Soul, <hi>Lovest thou me?</hi> What Anſwer could you make but this; <hi>Lord,</hi> I cannot ſay Thou loveſt me, <hi>(O that I could,)</hi> but, as far as I know my own Heart, I do love Thee, I deſire to love Thee, I would fain love Thee: I approve, eſteem, and judge thoſe the happieſt Souls, that love Thee moſt, and live in Thy Love. Oh, what would I not give, or do, or part with, if I might be One of them!</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reflections</hi> I would make on what has been ſaid, will concern two Sorts of Perſons, of a very different Character.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> I would Caution ſome, not to abuſe, or miſ-improve this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, by emboldening themſelves to come to the Lord's Table, in their Hypocriſie, and under the reigning Power of Sin. Let them not think that 'tis enough, if they can but make themſelves uncertain, whether they are Hypocrites, or no. There are ſome who have no Aſſurance of their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50599:26"/> Salvation; and it is impoſſible they ſhould; their State will not admit it: They are under the Dominion of Sin, and live in the Impurities of the Fleſh, and under the prevailing pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of an Earthly Mind, deſtitute of Love to God, and Strangers to Faith in Chriſt, and yet will adventure to come frequently to the Table of the Lord. 'Tis a terrible Paſſage, <hi>He that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh Damnation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> (Temporal Judgments and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity in many Caſes, Spiritual in others, and, without Repentance, Eternal,) which frightens <hi>Some</hi> from Communicating at all, which it ſhould not; but doth not deter <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> from coming unworthily, which it ſhould.</p>
            <p>There are divers ſuch, who thro' Sloth and Negligence, and Inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, for want of Enquiring into their true State, are ready to flatter themſelves, from ſome little things (as tranſient Affections in the publick Duties of Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) that their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50599:27"/> State is good, but they do not allow themſelves leiſure, to think what they are; and with many, the hurry of their Earthly Buſineſs will hardly permit them to retire, for Self-Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination: And yet they will come, they will do as others, and, without further ſearch, take it for granted, that they may and ought to come to the Table of the Lord. Sometimes they have checks of Conſcience, and if they think of Dying, are afraid; and well they may; there is reaſon for it. Such Profeſſors ſhould take heed of abuſing what hath been ſaid to Others, who need it. They like to hear, that many who have Doubts and Fears, concerning their State, may yet come to the Lord's Table; 'tis good News to them; for they have ſometimes Doubts, and <hi>no Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance,</hi> (nor will their preſent State allow it,) and yet they will adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Oh, beware how you miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and miſimprove, to your own Deſtruction, what hath been ſaid for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50599:27"/> the Encouragement and Support of Sincere Chriſtians, under Doubts, and Scruples, Weakneſs, and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Let ſuch conſider the Guilt they contract, and the unſpeakable Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard they run, by profeſſing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Chriſt's Family, and ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of His Supper, as Living Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of His Body, while they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Enemies unto Chriſt, in Heart and Life, and hate to be reform'd. Such are <hi>Guilty of His Body and Blood,</hi> they joyn with the Murderers of JESUS, whoſe Death they pretend to ſhew forth; His very Blood will cry for Vengeance againſt their Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, and ſink 'em under more dreadful and intolerable Wrath. They, of all others,
<hi>Eat and Drink their own Damnation,</hi> who thus wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully prophane the Ordinance, and take the Name of GOD in vain, by pretending Love to CHRIST, (to ſerve ſome little Secular turn, and be thought better than they are,) while
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50599:28"/> they Live in ſecret allow'd Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; in ſtated Enmity and Rebellion againſt Him.</p>
            <p>I may ſay of the Worthy or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Receiver, as <hi>Solomon</hi> did of <hi>Adonijah,</hi> 1 Kings 1.25. <hi>If he be a Worthy Man, not a Hair ſhall fall from his Head; but if Wickedneſs be found in him, he ſhall Dye.</hi> If you come to the Lord's Table humbly and peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently, in Obedience unto Chriſt, in ſuch a manner, and for ſuch holy Ends, as He hath appointed, you ſhall meet with Welcome, you ſhall be feaſted with the fat things of His Houſe, you ſhall partake of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of His Grace, and receive of His Fulneſs. But, if you come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sorrow for Sin, and without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution againſt it; if you come Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent, and Unreformed, without Deſires, and Purpoſes, and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to forſake Sin, and ſubdue Corruption, and be devoted to God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You increaſe your Guilt, you harden your Hearts the more, you
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50599:28"/> receive a Curſe inſtead of a Bleſſing, and will be more under the Power, and in the Poſſeſſion of the Devil. And <hi>You ſhall dye for't,</hi> unleſs Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Grace do timely prevent it, by your Repentance and Converſion. I cannot ſpeak with too much Terror to ſuch. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There be Others, Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Sincere, Weary and Heavy-laden, Contrite and Broken in Heart, who have many Doubts, and yet much Love, who Fear and Tremble if they come, and yet fear to tarry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. There are many Such who need this Encouragement. They have the Call of Chriſt, to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber His Dying Love; their Duty is plain; They ought to make an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture of Faith, as <hi>Peter</hi> (when un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to take any Fiſh) yet, at Chriſt's Command, let down the Net with aſtoniſhing Succeſs: Or, as the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ſaid to the Blind Man, <hi>Be of good Comfort, Ariſe, for the Maſter calleth thee,</hi> Mark x. Let Faith in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50599:29"/> the Authority of Chriſt, bring you to Remember His Death, this way; If you obey the Precept, you don't know the Succeſs as to Comfort.</p>
            <p>Is there no Encouragement in the Invitation, <hi>Let him that is a Thirst come, and Who Ever will, let him come, and take of the Waters of Life freely,</hi> Rev. xxii.
<hi rend="margQuotes">Are not ſenſible, weary, thirſty Sinners invited? Therefore, Lord, I'll not exclude my ſelf; I am one of them; ſurely there may be Mercy for Me, among the Reſt, however Unworthy and Vile I am.</hi> The Invitation is not to ſuch as are <hi>Worthy,</hi> but
<hi>Thirſty.</hi> We come to Him that we may partake of His Grace, and receive more of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Holineſs, according as we need it.</p>
            <p>And here, I would not forget the Caſe of Thoſe, who are in Doubts, becauſe they have had a
<hi>Religious Education,</hi> and by the Reſtraining Grace of God, and the Precepts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd into them, by their Parents
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50599:29"/> and Miniſters, they have liv'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blamably in the World, as to their outward Converſation: They are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, all their Religion is the Fruit of <hi>Education</hi> only; and not of <hi>Special Grace:</hi> And they are further doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful concerning themſelves, for want of feeling thoſe Pangs of Sorrow, and Bitter Repentance, which they hear, and read others have had, in their Converſion to God, who have been reclaim'd from a Proſtigate Life. They apprehend, on that account, that they may be ſtill Strangers to the great Change, by Regeneration and the New Birth. On the one hand; I wiſh they would look to it, that it be not really the Truth of their Caſe; that they have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed proceeded no further, than <hi>a good Education</hi> may carry a Man; which too many, I fear, do Reſt in. Yet Others there are, who have had a <hi>Religion Education,</hi> and, by God's Bleſſing on it, have had Early Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50599:30"/> of the diſtinguiſhing Grace of God. They can't ſay preciſely when they were Born again, but can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Effects of it in Heart and Life: Theſe ſhould not be diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on that account; Nor for want of thoſe Terrors, which the Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Converſion of Some is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd with Early Contents, who ſeek the Lord, and ſerve Him from their Youth, commonly eſcape ſuch Terrors: We find not, that 'tis true of All.</p>
            <p>If the Spirit of Chriſt hath wrought ſuch a Change in your Judgment, Choice, Affections, Conſcience, and Life, as will make up the Character of thoſe that are Sanctify'd; you ſhould not be uneaſie and perplex'd, for want of knowing <hi>when</hi> this Change was <hi>first</hi> made; you may know a Man is Alive tho' you know not when or when he was Born. And what if you cannot ſay thoſe things, concerning the Time, Manner, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedents, and Concommitants of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50599:30"/> your Converſion from Sin to God, that Others, it may be, can ſay, who had great and preſumptuous Sins, ſcandalous and notorious Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Repent of, which God never ſuffer'd you to fall into? Such are not ſufficiently ſenſible of the Bleſſing of a good <hi>Education,</hi> and what a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy it is to be ſav'd from ſuch Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. It may be, ſome of the Beſt Chriſtians in all this Nation are of this Sort; who may ſometimes fear they have gone no further than <hi>Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> (without the ſaving Grace of God) may lead
'em. But if you can prove your Sanctification, by the real, genuine Fruits of it; And that there is ſuch a Change of Heart and Life wrought, it matters not that you know not <hi>the exact Time.</hi> You are certain, Corrupt Nature could never incline you to love God, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to Him; to hate Sin and watch againſt it; and to take Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for your Portion and Chriſt for your Saviour: This Change muſt be
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50599:31"/> from the Divine Spirit, however Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Gradual, and Inſenſible it ſeems to have been Effected. If you find the Image of God upon your Souls, and the real Fruits of the Spirit in Heart and Life, (tho' you never were acquainted, with the Throws, and Pangs, and Terrors, that intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce or accompany the Converſion of others) you have Reaſon to be Thankful, and not be diſcourag'd on that account.</p>
            <p>Your great Buſineſs now, ſhould be to walk Circumſpectly, and to live more a Life of Faith and Love: And as your Faith in Chriſt, and Love to God, and Care to pleaſe Him, doth increaſe, Comfort, and Peace, and Joy, will ordinarily follow. <hi>The Juſt Live by Faith,</hi> not by <hi>Aſſurance.</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Faith</hi> 'tis impoſſible to pleaſe God, not without <hi>Aſſurance.</hi> You ought to obſerve God's Influence by His Holy Spirit upon your Souls; and be much in Prayer, and in acts of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance and Reſignation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50599:31"/> to know yourſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: To Record what God doth for you, and how you carry in towards Him, and what Progreſs you make in Practical Godlineſs, and Inward Religion; by comparing yourſelves with your Selves, at different times.</p>
            <p>Be thankful that you have good Hope, through Grace, and reſolve to follow on to know the Lord and to know your Selves better. Tho' it be our Duty to give all Diligence to make our Calling and Election ſure, and to uſe Means in Expectation of Succeſs, it is not at all ſtrange that but <hi>few</hi> do attain to <hi>Certainty</hi> and <hi>full Aſſurance.</hi> There muſt be more than a little Grade to make it clear and diſcernible; and 'tis Grace in Exerciſe is beſt diſcern'd: There muſt be a good underſtanding of Spiritual Things and of the Tenor of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace; ſome good Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with our own Hearts, and with the Wiles of the Devil; and ſome Cure of that confuſion and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50599:32"/> of Thought which moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of: There muſt be Diligence, Reſolution, and Patience, in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of our Selves, with earneſt Prayer to Heaven: There muſt be upright Walking a Pure Conſcience, and great fear of ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such things as theſe being neceſſary, in an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way is it any wonder that <hi>few,</hi> very <hi>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> attain it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When Grace is ſo weak, where it is true, and the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Selves ſo little, and moſt are ſo backward to Self-Examination, or ſo little skill'd in it, and ſo little acquainted with Satan's Temptations, and their Minde ſo confus'd, and their Thoughts ſo ungovern'd, and their Conſciences have ſo little Tenderneſs, and are ſo often wounded by wilful Sin, no wonder if the generality of Chriſtians have not <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> even of ſuch as are Sincere, and accepted of God.</p>
            <p>There are many things to be known and underſtood concerning the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Application of the Promiſes
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50599:32"/> of the Goſpel, which every real Chriſtian hath not attain'd. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the diſcerning of their own State and Condition to be ſuch, as that they may apply the Promiſes to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, there muſt be the Influence of <hi>the Holy Spirit,</hi> or there will be no Comfort. You muſt therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually beg the Light and Influence of the Holy Spirit, which is promiſed to Believers, that they may know the things freely given 'em of God. The Holy Spirit himſelf Witneſſeth with our Spirits, that we are the Children of God.
<hi rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Lord!</hi> I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to ſearch my Heart, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine my Ways, according to thy Command; I have ſome good Hope, but am not Certain; Oh enlighten me to diſcern and underſtand the Truth of my Caſe. Let me know, by Experience, the meaning of that Scripture, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13, 14. <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you believed, you were ſealed by the Spirit of Promiſe, which is the Earneſt of our Inheritance, until the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50599:33"/> Redemption of the purchaſed Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
               </hi> This <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> this <hi>Seal</hi> (for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, and for Certainty) God gives to Believers. 'Tis by the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit we know the things freely given us of God; by His witneſs with our Spirits, we have Confidence towards God, we diſcern His Work upon our own Souls, and are inabled to judge concerning the great Change he
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th made, and with Comfort to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, we are paſſed from Death to Life. The Teſtimony of the Divine Spirit, added to that of the Conſcience, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables us to cry, <hi>Alba Father,</hi> and fills us with Peace and Joy in Believing. <hi>He that believes, hath the witneſs within himſelf,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> John v. 10. He hath that
<hi>in him</hi> to which the Promiſes are made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath the Seal of <hi>Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> by which he is diſtinguiſh'd from Unbelievers; but the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit muſt diſcover and witneſs this, or we ſhall not feel any thing of Joy.
'Tis, in part, becauſe we do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, or value, or pray for, this
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50599:33"/> Influence of the Holy Spirit, as we ought, that ſo few have Aſſurance.</p>
            <p>And now, for the Cloſe of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, let me ask you a few ſerious Queſtions, which in many Books you may find more largely inſiſted on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> How ſtand you Affected to Sin, deliberate Sin, againſt God? Don't you dread and fear it more than formerly? Are you not more aſham'd of it, of the Baſeneſs, Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Diſingenuity of it, as againſt the Holineſs, and againſt the Grace, and Love of God? Would it not be a harder matter to draw you to a deliberate Sin againſt God, than here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore? or to perſwade you to omit a known Duty, ſuch as Cloſet Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> What is your Judgment and Opinion concerning God, and Chriſt, and Holineſs, concerning the Holy Scriptures, and the Goſpel way of Salvation, by Faith in Chriſt? Is it not more your Deſire, and Choice, to have your Portion, in both Worlds,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50599:34"/> with thoſe that believe on Chriſt, and follow Him, as their only Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our? Reſolving to adhere to reveal'd Chriſtian Religion, let <hi>Atheists</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> talk as they pleaſe, and venture as they will? Are you not endeavouring with ſucceſs to be more eſtabliſh'd in the great Foundation Truths of Chriſtianity?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Don't you find ſome Growth, Progreſs, and Improvement, in Holineſs, by being more confirm'd and eſtabliſh'd in the Truth of the Principles of Chriſtian Religion? And don't you deſire and endeavour more, to know, and do the Will of God? To pleaſe, and ſerve, and obey Him better? Is it not your Comfort and Pleaſure, to honour God, and be kept from Sin; to Worſhip and Adore Him, and have Communion with Him? To be found in the way of your Duty, and to keep an undefiled Conſcience? And is it not your Grief, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, when, by Temptation, you neglect your Duty to God, and fall into Sin?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:50599:34"/>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As to the Church of Chriſt, and the Intereſt and Honour of God in the World; are you not Rejoyc'd, when you hear that real Godlineſs is any where promoted? That the Oppreſſed, or Defiled Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt, are deliver'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd? That Truth and Holineſs, Pure Worſhip, and Holy Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, does prevail and ſpread, and get ground, in any part of the World, or of the Nation? That open Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs is ſuppreſs'd, and the Mouth of Iniquity ſtopp'd? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And, on the contrary, don't you mourn for other Men's Sins, as well as your own, and for God's Diſhonour, by Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Provocations, and Publick Crimes? And are ready to give what Aſſiſtance you can, to promote Reformation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> How are you Affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſuch as are truly Serious and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, tho' of different Sentiments, in ſeveral things, from you? Do you love the holy Image of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you can diſcern it? Can you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50599:35"/> heartily embrace All that love the Lord Jeſus in Sincerity? But for ſuch as Defie God, and Diſhonour Chriſt, and the Goſpel, and live in open Rebellion againſt Him, don't you, from your very Hearts, diſlike ſuch? you would not, you do not chuſe Familiarity with them; you would not live or dye with them? You have made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Choice, as to your Portion, Way, and End.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Can you bear to have your Conſciences ſearch'd? Are you content, to have your cloſeſt Luſts diſcover'd, your moſt belov'd Sins ſtruck at, by the Miniſtry of the Word? So that, there is no Iniquity but you would know, and hate, and part with? And are moſt of all deſirous, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie and overcome the Sin which you did once moſt love; and that did, or doth moſt eaſily beſet you: But 'tis your daily Burthen, that your Victory is ſo imperfect, and your dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Care is to watch againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:50599:35"/>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Is it not the Deſire, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and Reſolution of your Souls, tho' you have not <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> (and ſuppoſing you never had it, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhould,) that yet, by the Help of God, you will be true to your Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Covenant, to be faithful Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Chriſt, as long as you live; to deny all Ungodlineſs and World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Luſts, to live Soberly, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and Godly, in this World, ſeeking Glory, and Honour, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, by Jeſus Chriſt, in hopes of Eternal Life; depending on no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Saviour; looking for Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God no other Way, but only by the Merit, Blood, Sacrifice, and Righteouſneſs, of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt? This you unfeignedly Reſolve and Purpoſe, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (notwithſtanding your Doubts and Fears) you have held on for ſome time in ſuch a Courſe; and, by the Grace of God, do intend ſtill to hold on, whether you have Aſſurance or No.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:50599:36"/>To ſuch of You, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> who can truly ſay, this is your Caſe: That all, or any thing conſiderable of this, is a true and real part of your Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter: I may ſay, that Peace and Comfort belongs to you. The breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Faith argue the Reality of it, as much as the loudeſt Voice. To be able to creep, is as true an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Life, as to be able to run. You may lift up your Head with Hope, and avouch the Lord to be your God; you may come to the Lord's Table with Chearfulneſs and Thankſgiving. I do, in the Name of my Great Maſter, invite you: I doubt not but He will bid you Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
            <p>O let us All joyn, in begging His Gracious Preſence! That He would meet us Here, and in every part of the City and Country, where this Holy Feaſt, on the Sacrifice of Chriſt, ſhall be celebrated to Morrow!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:50599:36"/>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">O that He would diſplay the Banner of His Love towards Us! and Seal His Covenant-Promiſe, with all the Sweetneſs, and Joy of His Salvation, unto our Souls! O that He would ſpeak by His Holy Spirit, to our Spirits, with ſuch a Powerful Voice, as ſhall make us hear, and feel it, that it is <hi>His own!</hi> ſaying, Son, or Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, be of good Cheer, thy Sins are forgiven thee. I AM THY GOD, I have loved thee with an Everlaſting Love, I have accepted thee for mine; I have blotted out all thy numerous, hainous Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and will remember 'em no more; <hi>I enter'd into Covenant with thee, and thou becamest mine;</hi> and I am not aſhamed to be cal- THY GOD, <hi>I will never, never, never,</hi> leave thee nor forſake thee, but Guide thee by my Counſel, and afterwards receive thee to Glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
